VIII

Each year the pencil marks to show how much the children had grown crept up and up by the side door, like a rising tide. And then Maggie‚Äôs stopped rising, and she was a grown-up young lady; though you wouldn‚Äôt have known it from seeing her in the morning, in her shabby old dress, up in the cherry tree helping Albert pick cherries, or galloping around the meadow bare-back on Stella, or, in the woods, pulling off her stockings and dew-soaked shoes to wade knee-deep with Victor in the foam-flecked brown brook.

But, when they drove to evening parties, or rolled up their own parlor carpet and sprinkled candle-shavings over the floor, she blossomed out with bustle and chignon, high heels and long ear-rings; and every bit of her was young lady then, except the little boy feelings inside of her.

The world was flowing in on them‚ÅÝ‚Äîhere a little trickle, there a rush. So many more people than there used to be, and so much to do! Dancing and picnics and tableaux‚ÅÝ‚Äîoh, life was such fun!

May tried to pull Mamma‚Äôs gown together at the waist while Mamma looked Maggie and Lily over. She knew May would be all right, but the other two were so careless.

Maggie‚Äôs straight brown hair was parted in the middle, and brushed, sleek as satin, over a huge bun of chignon. Her cream and brown striped silk dress cocked up like a wren‚Äôs tail behind in a big bustle, and then cascaded off into a little train, and Mamma had lent her a lace frill for her open collar.

Lily was in blue, to match her eyes, and her fair flowing hair, crimped except just at the ends from its tight braiding, was pushed back of ears from which dangled balls of silver filigree as big as cherries. Both the girls looked very neat‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut, oh dear, what big waists, thought Mamma with a sigh. May was the only one who managed to have a wasp waist. She didn‚Äôt mind how hard they pulled her corset strings. Holding on to the bed post, drawing in her breath, she would get Lily to pull on them with all her strength. She didn‚Äôt care how much too small her high-heeled slippers were, either, just so she could squeeze her feet into them. Feeling like the princess in the fairy tale who walked barefoot over fire and swords, she would dance all evening, laughing and talking, though when she got home she would burst into tears from pain and exhaustion.

‚ÄúDon‚Äôt slouch, Lily. Will you ever learn to stand properly?‚Äù sighed Mamma.

‚ÄúWell, but Mamma dear! I do get so tired doing that old Grecian bend!‚Äù

‚ÄúWell, remember to when you‚Äôre in company, or I shall die of mortification. Back up to me, Maggie, your pannier‚Äôs crooked. Now don‚Äôt fidget‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúPull in, Mamma!‚Äù said May, tugging at Mamma‚Äôs grey satin. ‚ÄúThere! Oh, I wish you‚Äôd let me have a low body like yours‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI hate these old high necks!‚Äù

Mamma took a placid look in the mirror at her bosom and shoulders bulging out of her black lace and grey ruching‚ÅÝ‚Äîbulging, but with such delicious creaminess. She tried to keep her mouth from quirking up at the corners as she remembered that Mr.¬ÝAlfred Lacey had told his gentlemanly sister Mrs.¬ÝThornton, who good-naturedly told Mamma, that he had never seen finer shoulders. She wondered if he would be there tonight‚ÅÝ‚Äîperhaps she‚Äôd better wear her garnet necklace. The dark red made her bosom look even whiter.

‚ÄúAnyway, you might let me have some evening hair,‚Äù May complained, pouting, her mouth a bunched red bud. She was the beauty of the family, with her long lashes and deep warm coloring, her tiny waist and round little bosom; but her hair wouldn‚Äôt grow long. It just foamed in short curls all over her head, looking so silly and babyish. If only Mamma would let her have some coronet braids or a rippling switch to flow over her shoulder! But Mamma would only laugh and pinch her cheek gently and say fifteen was too young for evening hair.

Young and warm together under the buffalo robes, while the sleigh-bells rang‚ÅÝ‚Äîmerry‚ÅÝ‚Äîmournful‚ÅÝ‚Äîthey drove from all over the country for miles around, over the snow to the party.

Lily liked best to play the piano while the others danced. She felt shy and awkward, sitting waiting to be asked, not knowing whether she was more afraid that some one would ask her, or that no one would. She could play ‚ÄúWater Lily Waltz‚Äù and ‚ÄúOver the Waves‚Äù pretty well, and parts of lots of others; but she was a conscientious performer, and when she played parts wrong she would stop and say, ‚ÄúOh dear! Wait a minute!‚Äù and play them over again. It was a relief to the dancers when some good-natured mother would shoo her off the piano-stool.

‚ÄúNow then, Lily Campion! Run and have a good time with the young people!‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, I don‚Äôt mind playing, Mrs.¬ÝAusten, really I don‚Äôt.‚Äù

But she would go docilely, and waltz with kind fathers and little brothers. And often Mamma‚Äôs new friend Mr.¬ÝLacey would give her a turn, bounding as lightly as a balloon on his neat little feet.

Or they all went skating together. Oh, how beautifully the young gentlemen skimmed over the ice, cutting grape-vines and figure eights, leaning far over with one leg stuck out behind, showing off to the girls, who glided demurely about with their little hats with pheasant feathers and cascading veils pitched over their noses, and their tiny muffs held tight to their waists beneath their rounded busts.

Maggie skated beautifully‚ÅÝ‚Äîtoo well to charm the gentlemen. Victor and his young friends darted about like water-bugs, using the others for bases and bumpers. Lily was fat and her ankles were weak, so she stood on the side of her feet and watched the others, most of the time. As for May, the part she liked best was having her skates put on.

‚ÄúWhat tiny feet!‚Äù

‚ÄúOh, now you‚Äôre making fun of me, and I think it‚Äôs downright mean in you!‚Äù

‚ÄúNo, I‚Äôm not, on my honor, I never saw such little feet.‚Äù

‚ÄúGoodness, I don‚Äôt see why you think my feet are little! I think they‚Äôre huge! Yes, I do! Truly!‚Äù

Between winter and spring came Lent. They all went to church for the Litany every Wednesday evening; and the Campion girls gave up candy. Lily gave up desserts, too, because she loved them so. She would stand looking at a charlotte russe or a Bavarian cream on the sideboard until she couldn‚Äôt bear it another minute and had to rush away, out of temptation. Once, halfway through Lent, she fell. Putting what was left of the Bavarian cream into the slide on Martha‚Äôs evening out, she seized a tablespoonful and crammed it into her mouth. But between her haste and the size of the mouthful and her shame at breaking her promise to Lord Jesus, she nearly choked to death.

Then out from the long dark tunnel of Lent into the brightness of Easter. The parlor fragrant with Mamma‚Äôs fat sausage-shaped hyacinths of creamy pink and silvery blue‚ÅÝ‚Äîfat ladies with beautiful souls‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe eggs that had been boiled tied up in bits of colored calico that dyed them in such charming splotches and blots of color. Victor and Lily ate four apiece for breakfast on Easter morning, and Maggie ate two, but Mamma and May were delicate, and only had one each. And then they drove to church, to sing, happy and self-conscious in their new straw hats:

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòThe strife is o‚Äôer, the battle done;

The victory of life is won;

The song of triumph has begun.

Alleluia!‚Äô‚Ää‚Äù

Mr.¬ÝLacey sang away in his pew, too, so tidy, so shining, with his pink face, his kind round blue eyes and silky nut-brown whiskers, his neat gloves and beautifully laundered linen, that he looked as if he must be kept under a glass bell from Sunday to Sunday. And as soon as church was over he came hurrying out to help Mamma into the carriage.

When summer came, they all went sailing, and had picnic suppers on the Jersey shore. The girls in their blue flannel boating costumes unpacked the baskets, and made coffee over the driftwood fires the young men built, and pretended they were very busy and mustn‚Äôt be bothered. ‚ÄúAh-h-h‚Äù sighed the little waves, coming in over the sand, drawing back. ‚ÄúAh-h-h‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù The breeze brought them the river smell‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe cool wet smell of mud and reeds and soaking rotten wood; and over the Delaware hills the sunset deepened, violet, orange and rose. One white star trembled. Victor raced along the shore. Other little boys might be left at home, but not he. He found a dead crab, and chased the girls with it‚ÅÝ‚Äîugh! the smelly thing!

And everyone was so funny.

‚ÄúDoes your mother know you‚Äôre out?‚Äù they called to each other; and oh, the laughter when some young lady would cry, ‚ÄúWe‚Äôve forgotten the spoons!‚Äù The very word spoon, the sight of a spoon, was enough to send the young men off into fits of laughter, while the girls tried to look innocent and demure.

Sailing home through the moonlight the laughter would grow gentle, would die.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòMy Bonny lies over the ocean,

My Bonny lies over the sea,

My Bonny lies over the ocean;

Oh, bring back my Bonny to me!‚Äô‚Ää‚Äù

Swish, swish! The liquid moon-silver flowed gently, strongly back from the bow of the boat, and young hands groped for young hands, and found them.

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòBring back, bring back,

Oh, bring back my Bonny to me‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚ÅÝto me!

Bring back, bring back,

Oh, bring back my Bonny to me!

¬Ý

‚Äú‚Ää‚ÄòLast night, as I lay on my pillow,

Last night, as I lay on my bed,

Last night, as I lay on my pillow,

I dreamt that my Bonny was dead!‚Äô‚Ää‚Äù

And it would have been too sweet, too sad to bear if some one had not sung, mock-tragically:

‚ÄúOh, bring back my Bonny, and don‚Äôt be so funny‚ÅÝ‚Äî!‚Äù

XXV

вҖңYou mark my words, LilyвҒ вҖ”Wadsworth Robinson is going to make May an offer, and whatвҖҷs more, I believe sheвҖҷs going to take him. LookвҒ вҖ”heвҖҷs really not bad lookingвҒ вҖ”not handsome, but kind of niceвҒ вҖ”вҖқ

Lily joined Maggie in gazing out from behind a pinch back of bedroom window curtain. Mr.В Robinson propped his bicycle against a tree, took off the clips that held his white tennis trousers tight around his ankles, straightened a small white hat above his serious red-brown face, and took a box from the net hammock on his handlebars. вҖңChocolates,вҖқ said Lily.

May had been watching, too, with a feeling of fingers closing around her heart, squeezing it lightly. Her knees trembled and she felt suddenly weak, and had to sit down on her bed a momentвҒ вҖ”had to fling herself down with her face in the pillow.

She knew that he loved her, that he was going to ask her to marry him. And she was going to marry him. She shook with fascinated terror, dark excitement. This way, alone, with her face pressed into the pillow, she loved him.

She got up, patted a dust of powder over her flaming cheeks, and ran downstairs, and her sisters heard her company voice cry:

вҖңWhy, I didnвҖҷt know you were here! IsnвҖҷt it a heavenly day for tennis? VictorвҖҷs gone over for Daisy, theyвҖҷll be here soon, I guess.вҖқ

If only he had gone on from the place he had reached in her dream! Already she had taken him past the need of words. But he was himself, so much less real to her than her idea of him.

вҖңIt certainly is a beautiful day! IвҖҷm looking forward to our game of tennis very much.вҖқ

вҖңVery muchвҖқ! Oh, oh, how tepid! And yet there was nothing tepid in the way he was looking at her. Wings fluttered in her breast, and her voice changed from company voice to a light shaken chime of bells, the secret of life escaped through it, though the words it was crying were only:

вҖңOh, for me? Oh, you shouldnвҖҷt haveвҒ вҖ”chocolates!вҖқ

вҖңAnd bonbons,вҖқ he pointed out.

Victor and Daisy played against May and Mr.В Robinson. May felt like a soap-bubble, bounding, gleaming, bright color swirling into bright color. Mr.В Robinson couldnвҖҷt take his eyes off her, he never even looked at Daisy, except abstractedly, as if she were a cow or a tree. His faithful dog eyes followed May, you could almost see a loving tail wagging.

вҖңStay to supper,вҖқ Maggie invited him and Daisy. She didnвҖҷt want Daisy, but she couldnвҖҷt ask one and not the other.

вҖңOh, my dear! Rapture and bliss if there was any way of letting my old Sambo knowвҒ вҖ”heвҖҷs feeling kind of mean, and most likely heвҖҷs in bed and asleep; still, I guess I ought to send word. Our telephone would certainly be a lot more useful if any other of the folks out here had one.вҖқ

вҖңIвҖҷll go over on my bicycle,вҖқ suggested Mr.В Robinson in his deep serious voice, вҖңAnd tell Mother on the way that I wonвҖҷt be home either.вҖқ

вҖңOh, would you? Angel of light and mercy! IвҖҷll love you for life!вҖқ

вҖңThereвҖҷs a moon tonight,вҖқ said Mr.В Robinson in a voice vibrating with meaning. He only meant May to hear, but Daisy heard too, and burst into screams of laughter as he pedalled out of the drive, ringing his bicycle bell to the empty road.

вҖңвҖҠвҖҳThereвҖҷs a moon tonight,вҖҷвҖҠвҖқ she mimicked, deep in her throat. вҖңOw! I shall die! May, heвҖҷs going to propose! WouldnвҖҷt you know heвҖҷs the kind of fellow wouldnвҖҷt think a proposal was legal unless it was by moonlight?вҖқ

вҖңOh, donвҖҷtвҒ вҖ”!вҖқ cried Maggie.

вҖңOw! Ow! My side! Where did he get that hat?вҖқ

вҖңвҖҠвҖҳWhere did you get that hat?вҖҷвҖҠвҖқ sang Victor, and he picked up a little white paper bonbon case from Mr.В RobinsonвҖҷs box, put it on his head, seized LilyвҖҷs palm leaf fan, and gave an imitation of him playing tennis that made them laugh until they cried.

вҖңOh! Oh!вҖқ May was nearly sobbing. вҖңDid you ever see anything so much too small as it was, and so white, and so new! If it hadnвҖҷt been so new! But it might just as well have had вҖҳBought for the occasionвҖҷ printed all over it in large black lettersвҒ вҖ”oh! I shall never be able to keep a straight face when I look at him againвҒ вҖ”вҖқ

And she laughed and laughed, with the tears rolling down her cheeks, until she was almost screamingвҒ вҖ”faint, sobbing screams, like something dying.

The moon turned the river to silver silk and showed frills of white flowers edging the garden paths. The air was drenched with moonlight and fragrance. And all evening May kept close to Victor and Daisy in the garden, though they certainly didnвҖҷt want her. But she wasnвҖҷt going to be left alone with that silly, solemn thingвҒ вҖ”вҒ

Maggie could stop worrying about Daisy, for she had gone awayвҒ вҖ”gone away forever. Cousin Sam doubled up groaning one day on his old leather sofa, said to her, trying to smile, вҖңDonвҖҷt you worry, honey,вҖқ and died. And Daisy cried as if her heart were broken, and, covered with crГӘpe, yards and yards and yards of crГӘpe, went back to New York as fast as she could go, hardly stopping long enough to say goodbye, even to Victor. Meadowbrook was sold to strangers now.

A year later they saw her picture in вҖңTypes of Fair WomenвҖқ in MunseyвҖҷs Magazine, and learned that she had married again. His sisters were afraid Victor would mind, and tried to break it to him gently, but he had heard it already and didnвҖҷt seem to mind at all.

вҖңWell, thatвҖҷs a relief!вҖқ thought Maggie, and yetвҒ вҖ”how could he be so cheerful, when he had seemed really to love Daisy? вҖңVictorвҖҷs unselfish,вҖқ she told herself. вҖңWhen heвҖҷs unhappy he keeps it to himself.вҖқ

For a few hours they were excitedвҒ вҖ”but God performed again his miracle of changing the water into wine, as the summer rains were bottled in the purple and pale-green globes of the grapes; the frost killed MaggieвҖҷs dahlias; Lily scalded her hand; the organ-grinder came, playing his hollow plaintive tune and jerking his monkey on its chainвҒ вҖ”there were other things to think of happening all the time. They seemed so importantвҒ вҖ”and then they were over, and no one remembered them at all.

For the second time the thunder of war came to the CampionsвҒ вҖ”more distant now, in Cuba. War with Spain was declared at the end of AprilвҒ вҖ”too beautiful a time for people to be fighting, Maggie thought, pulling down an apple-tree branch and snuffing at the red buds and rose and silver blossoms. Still, one must remember the вҖңMaine.вҖқ Victor was always singing about it.

вҖңвҖҠвҖҳSpain, Spain, Spain,

Why arenвҖҷt you ashamed?

Why, why, why,

For blowing up the Maine?

One, two, three,

And Cuba will go free,

ThereвҖҷll be a hot time

In the old town

Tonight!вҖҷвҖҠвҖқ

How terrible it must be there for our poor soldiers. The sisters, looking through the dim windows of the newspapers, saw palm trees against quivering blue, and small lizards with flickering tongues darting across earth cracked open with the heat, across men who lay too still to frighten them. And men were dying of thirst and feverвҒ вҖ”that was worse than having a bullet sing home to your heart. It seemed cruel to sit on the shady porch, drinking cold water, throwing what was left over the rail onto the lily-of-the-valley bed. And yet it was so hard to realize. It was as if the newspapers had made up a series of exciting stories.

вҖңIsnвҖҷt it dreadful?вҖқ the Campions would say solemnly, reading, and then, kindling, вҖңWell for pit-tyвҖҷs sakeвҒ вҖ”Raymond LineвҖҷs going to marry that Dawson girl with the funny nose!вҖқ Or Mrs.В Kelsey was advertising for a cook, or, most exciting of all, VictorвҖҷs name appeared. вҖңLook, May! Look, Maggie! HereвҖҷs Victor in again! вҖҳMr.В and Mrs.В Edgar H. Snare entertained a merry party of young people in honor of their daughter Miss Lola at a picnic supper on the banks of the beautiful Brandywine, those enjoying their hospitality includingвҖҷвҒ вҖ”mmвҒ вҖ”mmвҒ вҖ”hereвҒ вҖ”вҖҳMr.В V. ChampionвҖҷвҒ вҖ”Champion! How idiotic! WouldnвҖҷt you think theyвҖҷd know by this time? TheyвҖҷve had him in often enough. Where are the scissors? I want to cut it out for him.вҖқ

Yes, it was hard really to feel that a war was going on, although old ladies named their canaries вҖңDewey,вҖқ men cheerfully whistled вҖңGoodbye, Dolly, I must leave you,вҖқ and вҖңJust as the sun went down,вҖқ and little boys turned their hats up in front and were Rough Riders, shouting вҖңGiddap!вҖқ to their bicycles, and hissing beds of red and yellow cannas because they were SpainвҖҷs colors.

вҖңDid you ever know May had a friend named Allen Jermayne?вҖқ Lily asked Maggie.

вҖңNo, I never heard of him.вҖқ

вҖңShe says heвҖҷs fighting, heвҖҷs a captain, a West Point man. She says she hasnвҖҷt any photograph of him, that he never would have one taken, but she has a drawing of a Gibson man she says is the image of him. She acts awfully funny about it. I havenвҖҷt seen any letters from Cuba, have you? But she showed me a whole pile tied up with blue ribbon, and I could just see вҖҳMy loveliestвҖҷ something or other before she pulled them away. And she showed me some flowers he sent her from San Juan HillвҒ вҖ”she said they were tropical flowers.вҖқ

вҖңWhat like?вҖқ

вҖңSort of like pressed poppies.вҖқ

вҖңWell, sheвҖҷs been tearing up for the mail every dayвҒ вҖ”we wouldnвҖҷt have seen them. Oh, Lily, I do wishвҒ вҖ”Allen Jermayne! A. J.! I do believe thatвҖҷs the man she danced with all evening that time she had such fun in Wilmington, ages and ages ago. I think it was A. J.вҖқ

вҖңIвҖҷm going to be married as soon as the war is over,вҖқ May told them one day. вҖңIвҖҷm going to marry Captain Allen Jermayne.вҖқ And Maggie, feeling as if a fist had crashed between her eyes, knew that May was lying even before she turned scarlet and burst into tears.

Even Lily didnвҖҷt believe it. And May only pretended half-heartedly. She told them one day that Captain Jermayne had been killed, and she wore a black dress and let the others go for the mail once more. After that none of them ever spoke of it again.